<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Jerusalems fall, Englands warning ... of Gods word.]</title>
            <author>F. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21491.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132056</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73099)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2050:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Jerusalems fall, Englands warning ... of Gods word.]</title>
                  <author>F. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. S[nodham]. for T. Pavior [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Wrath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Word of God (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:132056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132056:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>IERVSALEMS FALL, Englands warning.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVK. 15.41.42.43.44.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 41.</hi>
                     </bibl> And when he was come neere, he beheld the Citie, and wept for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>42.</hi>
                     </bibl> Saying: O, if thou hadſt euen knowne, at the leaſt, in this thy day, thoſe thing which belong vnto thy peace, but, now are they hid from thine eyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>43.</hi>
                     </bibl> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the dayes ſhall come vpon thee, that thine enemies ſhall caſt a trench about thee, and compaſſe thee round, and keepe thee in or euery ſide.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>44.</hi>
                     </bibl> And ſhall make thee euen with the ground, and thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de which are in thee, and they ſhall not leaue in thee a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vpon a ſtone, becauſe thou kneweſt not the time of thy viſitation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter conſiſteth of foure parts: the firſt containeth the calling of <hi>Zacheus;</hi> the ſecond includeth the Parable of the <hi>Noble man</hi> deliuering his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to his Seruants, to occupy till his returne; the third, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth the manner of <hi>Christs</hi> riding to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 21.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with his Diſciples and much people, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132056:2"/> laid their garments on the Aſſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> on which our Lord Ieſus did ride, with great ioy and loud acclamations. The fourth and laſt, is the purging and clenſing of the <hi>Temple,</hi> of corruptions crept in and allowed by the Phariſies. The third part I haue choſen to intreat of, wherein the Euangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> declareth the great ioy, triumph, and reioycing of the Diſciples and people, with their loud acclamations, as they approached neere to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> in which action they were directed by the holy Ghoſt; that the Propheſie of <hi>Zachariah</hi> might be fulfilled, which was this: <hi>Reioyce greatly O daughter Zion: ſhout for ioy, O Daughter Ieruſalem: behold, thy King commeth vnto thee: he is iuſt and ſaued himſelfe, poore, and riding vpon an Aſſe, and vpon a colt, the ſoule of an Aſſe, Zacha.</hi> 9.9. Yet our Lord Ieſus, approching neere vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and beholding it, and withall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluing in his minde the great mercies of God, offered by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and now by <hi>him,</hi> and conſidering how the hearts of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were obdurate and hardned, and their eyes blinded, that they could neither ſee the grace offered, nor beleeue the promiſes made vnto them; he burſt forth into weeping, wiſhing that they <hi>had knowne the things that concerned their pence;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not, hee did Propheſie the vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Citie, and of their policie; which came to paſſe about ſome fortie yeeres after, and remaineth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day: which is an admonition to vs, and to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages, to beware and take heede that we doe not deſpiſe the grace of God, leſt we taſt of his iudgements. But I come to the words themſelues, which offer to our conſideration two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. An <hi>Admonition</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A <hi>Propheſie</hi> of the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt part of my text containeth an <hi>Admonition</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> wherein our Lord Ieſus warned her of her preſent eſtate, to draw her to a diligent conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132056:2"/> of the great mercy of God ſhewed vnto her. Firſt in ſending his Prophets: Secondly in ſending his Son to allure her vnto repentance, that ſhe might haue auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the iudgements and plagues which were immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and hung ouer her head, and afterwards fell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her.</p>
            <p>Wherein we may obſerue the great mercie of God, admoniſhing her of the danger that ſhe ſhould fall into, if ſhe did not preuent it by true and vnfained repentance. God giues a Cauent before his Capias, and doth warne before he doth wound. And thus the Lord hath done from the beginning; admoniſhing men either immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, or mediately, before of the danger, that auoiding it, they might eſcape the puniſhment. He admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, immediately by himſelfe, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the danger and puniſhment if he did eate of <hi>the Tree of knowledge of good and euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>in the middeſt of the Garden: Thou ſhalt die the death.</hi> He likewiſe warned <hi>Cain,</hi> before he murdered <hi>Abell</hi> his Brother, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by himſelfe: <hi>If thou doe well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhalt thou not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? if thou doeſt not well, ſinne lieth at the doore.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he forewarned <hi>Noah</hi> of the drowning of the world immediately by himſelfe,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.8.</note> who beleeued and eſcaped the mercileſſe waters. He admoniſhed, immediately,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.1.</note> by meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the old world by <hi>Noah,</hi> the eight Preacher of righteouſneſſe. He admoniſhed the <hi>Sodomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai</hi> by <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.5.</note> the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Niniuites</hi> by <hi>Ionah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> often before they were led into captiuitie, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by the <hi>Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math 23.</note> and by our Lord Ieſus, as here Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer things are written before time, are written for our learning.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the admonitions, comminations, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of puniſhments is in the Scriptures are therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, that in all times and ages they ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and preached vnto men, as teſtimonies of the iudgements of God againſt all impenitent ſinners, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132056:3"/> ſtop their eares at the voice of God, wincke with their eyes, that they may not ſee the mercies of God, and harden their hearts, not beleeuing his threatnings: Therefore our Lord Ieſus denounceth a heauie woe againſt <hi>Chorazin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Bethſaida</hi> and <hi>Capernaum,</hi> telling them that it ſhould be eaſier for <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> and for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> then for them in the day of iudgement. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewing how God ſlew three and twentie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for committing fornication decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> that all <hi>thoſe things came vnto them for examples, and were written to admoniſh vs, vpon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.18. This ſhall be written for the Generation to come.</note>This Admonition then vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and all other Admonitions in the Scriptures, are recorded in the Scriptures to be Preached vnto all men, to all Nations, to all eſtates and conditions of men, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to thoſe to whom the Goſpell hath beene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it might be an example of the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and an Admonition to Repentance, leſt they likewiſe deſpiſing the riches of Gods goodneſſe, patience, and long-ſuffering, according to their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and heart that cannot repent, they heape vp wrath againſt the day of wrath,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> and iuſt iudgement of God. This Admonition then concerneth vs, and warneth vs in time to repent, and to lay hold on the day of grace, before the day of iudgement come. The Goſpell hath beene preached vnto vs many yeeres, God hath beſtowed many fauours and benefits vpon vs, he hath giuen vs a long peace, hee hath defended vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our enemies, that are more in number and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then we; he hath made vs his vineyard, and bedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs round about, that the wilde Bore of the forreſt could not roote vs vp; he hath done as much, yea, much more for vs then for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he hath called vs to repentance by his ſeruants, the Miniſters and Preachers of the Goſpell: All the examples of Gods
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132056:3"/> iudgements in the Scriptures haue beene red and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto vs, yet we generally liue in ſecuritie, neither ſuſpecting any change, nor fearing any puniſhment: But let vs take heede that our Halcion-dayes doe not deceiue vs; neither let vs thinke that we are priuiledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aboue others:<note place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> For if God ſpared not the naturall branches, when they did not repent, will he ſpare vs that were wilde Oliues? The <hi>Iewes</hi> in the time of <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who dwelled in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> liued in great ſecuritie (as we doe) neither regarding Gods mercies, nor fearing his iudgements; therefore the Lord ſent <hi>Ieremiah</hi> with this meſſage vnto them. <hi>Behold I begin to plague the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie where my name is called vpon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhould you goe free? yee ſhall not goe quite, for I will call for a ſword vpon all the inhabitants of the earth.</hi> Euen ſo this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yea, and all the examples before mentioned doe preach vnto vs to turne vnto God, not flattering our ſelues that we are better then they; nay, I feare that our ſinnes are growne ſo great, that we haue iuſtified <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yea, <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> in their ſinnes; and therefore I ſay from the mouth of Chriſt vnto you, <hi>except ye repent, ye ſhall likewiſe periſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now out of this generall, let vs obſerue theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that it is Gods great mercy without mans deſert, to admoniſh and warne ſinners of their future puniſhments; if they refuſe his grace offered; he hath mercie on whom he will. When God then doth warne a Nation, a Countrie, a People, or Citie, he declareth his great mercie, <hi>That he would not the death of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but rather that he ſhould turne and liue.</hi> This mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God ſhould leade vs to repentance; it ſhould breake our ſtonie hearts, and ſoften the hardneſſe of them, when God ſpreadeth out his hands vnto vs, and offereth to gather vs together as a Henne doth her Chickens, that wee periſh not with the wicked.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:132056:4"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, all the Admonitions in the Scriptures are written for vs, to warne vs to preuent the wrath of God, and to eſcape the puniſhments of the wicked. Therefore when either we reade, or heare, how God deſtroyed a Nation, a People, a Country, yea, or ſome particular perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o deſpiſing his grace, and reiecting his admonition; let vs preſently apply it vnto our ſelues in this manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I reade, or I heare, how <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and other Cities, were deſtroyed, for refuſing the grace of God offered vnto them, I heare how ſuch men were ſeuerely puniſhed, when they would not be warned: If I doe not make vſe of this, the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will fall vpon me, therefore I will pray vnto God to grant me his grace, that I may take theſe warnings, and ſpeedily turne to God, that the fall of others may be my riſing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, theſe Admonitions will leaue vs without excuſe: For what can we plead for our ſelues, when ſo many examples and admonitions haue beene remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred vnto vs? He that is once warned, is halfe armed: therefore there remaineth no excuſe for vs, if we deſpiſe theſe admonitions, but a fearefull expectation of the iuſt iudgement of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, theſe Examples and Admonitions in the Scriptures, will be ſo many witneſſes againſt vs, and will riſe vp in iudgement to condemne vs: It ſhall be eaſier for <hi>Ieruſalem, Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> and for <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gamorha</hi> in the day of Iudgement, then for vs. God Almightie giue vs grace to make a good vſe of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the words, in particuler, as they lie in order.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:132056:4"/>
               <head>And when he was come neere vnto the Citie.</head>
               <p>OVr Lord Ieſus, accompanied with his Diſciples and much people, reioycing with great triumph, approacheth to <hi>Ieruſalem: And when he was come neere vnto the Citie; he beheld it, and wept for it.</hi> He commeth to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to an ingratefull and a rebellious. Citie, from which he had iuſt cauſe to depart: for ſhe neither would receiue his Doctrine, nor beleeue his miracles: His Doctrine ſhe challenged not to be of God, his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles ſhe aſcribed to Sathan,<note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> to <hi>Belzabub</hi> the chiefe of the Diuels; his perſon ſhe contemned, <hi>is not this the Carpenters Sonne? art thou not a Samaritan?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> Yet our Lord Ieſus, paſſing by all theſe indignities, commeth vnto her, and leaueth nothing vnattempted to ſaue her; as he himſelfe by his owne words teſtified. <hi>O Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtonest them that are ſent vnto thee; how often would I haue gathered thee together as a Henne doth hir Chickens, and thou wouldeſt not.</hi> Behold here the loue of our Lord Ieſus to an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull and a rebellious people. This example of Chriſt doth teach all his Miniſters, yea, and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to open their bowels of mercie, euen towards the obſtinate, not raſhly to forſake them, and depart from them, and to giue them ouer; but rather to labour to winne them vnto Chriſt, and to omit no time, to ſpare no labour to effect it, and to bring it to paſſe. So did <hi>Noah</hi> labour with the old world, <hi>Lot</hi> with the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Moſes</hi> with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians, Samuel</hi> with <hi>Saul,</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> with the <hi>Iſraelites, Paul</hi> with the <hi>Iewes.</hi> But it may be obiected that it is in vaine and but labour loſt, <hi>to caſt pearles before Swine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and to giue that which is holy vnto Dogges.</hi> I anſwer, we ought not ſo to thinke by and by of ſuch as are obſtinate and ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, of ſuch as are froward and ſtubborne, for God can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132056:5"/> ſuddenly change them; <hi>Paul</hi> was a Perſecutor, a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13.</note> and an oppreſſour, but God tooke mercie vpon him; <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Zacheus</hi> were Publicans and Sinners when our Lord Ieſus called them; Therefore let vs doe our diligence, and commit the ſucceſſe vnto God: If they continue in their diſobedience, they are without excuſe, and their condemnation is the more iuſt: He that refuſeth light, is worthy to continue in darkeneſſe; he that reiecteth grace, deſerueth to abide the ſenſure of Iuſtice. If we with our admonitions and exhortations reclaime and winne them, we ſaue ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſoules from death,<note place="margin">Iames 5.19.20.</note> and couer a multitude of ſinnes, and wee our ſelues ſhall in the day of the reſurrection ſhine as the Starres in the firmament.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>He beheld the Citie.</head>
               <p>AS our Sauiour Chriſt approached neere vnto <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſo he beheld it, he looked vpon it, and reuoluing in his minde her blockiſhneſſe and ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, neither ſeeing, nor acknowledging Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, nor yet fearing his iudgements, he burſt forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to weeping. Now we may conſider his kindneſſe and loue towards <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that he looketh on her, that he beheld her, from whom he had iuſt cauſe to turne away his eyes; yet he beholdeth her, he doth not auert his face from her, as men turne their eyes from their enemies:<note place="margin">Luk. 10.33.</note> But he is that good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> who ſeeing the wounded man, is moued with great commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and compaſſion towards him, pittying his diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed caſe, and indeauouring to relieue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>This example is our inſtruction, teaching vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold obſtinate ſinners, to looke vpon them, pittying their miſerable eſtate, which they themſelues ſee not. When therefore wee behold the common Swearer, breaking forth into outragious oathes: When we ſee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132056:5"/> ſome prophane the holy Sabaoth of the Lord: When we looke vpon the common Drunkard, or vpon any other notorious ſinner, committing ſinne with a high hand, and acting it with greedineſſe, making no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinning: let vs be moued with compaſſion towards them that know not what they doe; they lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thinke of the iudgements that hang ouer their heads, if they repent not. Now as the beholding of a man in ſome ſharpe fit of ſickneſſe, or the looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome grieuous ſore or feſtered wound, extreamely payning the patient, doth draw compaſſion from vs; euen ſo ſhould wee be moued to pittie the miſerable eſtate of grieuous ſinners, who are ſicke and wounded with ſinne, and yet doe not feele it: And if we ſhould and ought to be moued with compaſſion towards the obſtinate, for their great miſeries that ſhall befall them; how much more ought we to pittie the godly in their diſtreſſes, croſſes, and afflictions,<note place="margin">Dilige iure bonos &amp; miſereſce ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>Boetius.</hi>
                  </note> whereof we are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times eye-witneſſes. Here then the Stoikes, and all that are without naturall affection, are to be reproued:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.12. Rom. 12.15:</note> They that are Gods elect haue put vpon them the bowels of mercy; they weepe with them that weepe, they remember them that are in bonds,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.3. Pro. 12.10.</note> as if they were bound with them; and them that are in affliction, as if they were afflicted in the body: But the wicked haue cruell hearts, they giue themſelues to caſe and pleaſure, as <hi>Amos</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">Amos 6.6.</note> and remember not the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And wept.</head>
               <p>AS our Lord Ieſus approached vnto Ieruſalem, ſo <hi>he beheld the Citie,</hi> and beholding it <hi>he wept for it.</hi> We reade that Chriſt wept thriſe: Firſt when he raiſed vp <hi>Lazarus;</hi> for when he came to the place where they had laid him, <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>And he wept, Ioh.</hi> 11.35.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132056:6"/> Secondly, he wept ouer Ieruſalem, as here we reade. Thirdly, in his Paſſion, as the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>which in the dayes of his fleſh, did offer vp Prayers and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, with strong cryings, and teares, vnto him that was able to ſaue him from death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſts loue.</note> 
                  <hi>and was alſo heard in that which he feared. Heb.</hi> 5.7. The teares of Chriſt expreſſe the affection of his loue, as doth a Father weeping ouer his diſobedient and diſſolute ſonne, for the miſerie that he fore-ſeeth will come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for his inordinate life. He delighteth in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, rather then in iudgement. He delighteth not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, no not in the deſtruction of the wicked; he would haue all men to be ſaued, and to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his truth:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4. Ezek. 18.32. <hi>The vſe.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He deſireth not the death of a ſinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then Chriſt weepe for the miſery and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the wicked, much more will his eares be open vnto the ſighes and groanes, to the Prayers and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of his poore members, who turne vnto him with true contrition and ſorrow of heart, and call vpon him with a liuely faith. This ſhould be remembred of vs, that it may comfort and incourage vs to approach vnto the throne of his grace in time of neceſſitie, that we may receiue mercy, and finde grace.</p>
               <p>Againe, if the teares of Chriſt doe not moiſten and mollifie our dry and hard hearts; if they doe not moue vs, and draw vs vnto Repentance, he in the end will puniſh our obſtinacie and hardneſſe of heart, and though we cry then, hee will not regard our weeping, becauſe we deſpiſed his teares. Let vs in the feare of God meditate on this godly motion, that it may leade vs vnto true and ſpeedy Repentance. Doeſt thou not know that this loue of Chriſt ſhould leade thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</p>
               <p>The teares of Chriſt alſo expreſſe vnto vs the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and griefe of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Chriſts dolor.</note> For being ſent of his Father to gather the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132056:6"/> ſeeing their obſtinacie and ſtubborneneſſe, deſpiſing his word, reproaching his miracles, and reiecting his grace, he could not refraine from weeping; he burſt forth into teares. This was the cauſe why he being touched with compaſſion, ſhewed his loue and his griefe, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for the imminent deſtruction of Ieruſalem. For when he conſidered that Ieruſalem was ordained of God, to be the holy ſeate, in the which the couenant of euerlaſting ſaluation ſhould abide, the ſanctuary, from whence ſaluation ſhould come to the whole world, it could not be but that he muſt needes greatly lament the deſtruction thereof: when alſo he ſaw the people to periſh miſerably, by their owne ingratitude and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, which was adopted to the hope of eternall life, it is no maruell if he could not refraine from teares. Now this affection in Chriſt was not counterfeit, it was not fained, farre be it from vs to admit any ſuch thought; but it was true,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> for we haue not an high Prieſt which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but he was in all things tempted, in like ſort as we, yet without ſinne: wherefore in all things it became him to be made like vnto his brethren (for he tooke the ſeede of <hi>Abraham</hi>) that he might be mercifull, and a faithfull high Prieſt in things concerning God, that he might make reconciliation for the ſinnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for in that he ſuffered, and was tempted,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.17.18.</note> he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</p>
               <p>This affection then of true ſorrow in Chriſt for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, is a notable teſtimony and a ſure proofe of his humanitie and manhood, and is ſufficient to conuince and confute <hi>Marcion</hi> and other Heretiques, denying that he was a true and naturall man. And in this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, expreſſed by his wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for Ieruſalem, we haue a true patterne of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affections: weeping for Ieruſalem, a ſtubborne Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a diſobedient Citie, an vnfaithfull Citie. O ſhould
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132056:7"/> not this moue vs? O ſhould not this draw vs to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction? O ſhould not this pull vp the ſluces and floodgates of our eies, &amp; giue them free paſſage to guſh out with teares? Our Lord Ieſus wept, and can our eyes be dry to heare it?<note place="margin">Quis talia fandoi temperet à lacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis?</note> 
                  <hi>Virgill</hi> the Heathen Poet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the lamentable deſtruction of <hi>Troy,</hi> that was ſacked by the <hi>Graecians</hi> after ten yeares Seege, ſaith, <hi>who ſpeaking of theſe things, can refraine from teares?</hi> So ſay I, who is it that readeth or heareth how our Lord Ieſus wept, and can paſſe away with dry eyes?</p>
               <p>Now theſe teares of Chriſt did intimate that the ſinnes of Ieruſalem were greater; and the calamities and puniſhments imminent, and hanging ouer her head, were more grieuous then Ieruſalem did thinke or vnderſtand: for it is a great matter that good men ſpeake with teares. The ſequell did verifie this in the deſtruction of Ieruſalem: Our Lord Ieſus weepeth for the ſinnes of Ieruſalem, and for the puniſhments and calamities that ſhould come vpon her.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The vſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.7.8.</note>This example teacheth vs to weepe for the ſinnes of others: Righteous <hi>Lot</hi> had his ſoule vexed with the vncleane conuerſation of the wicked <hi>Sodomites.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 24.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> crieth out, <hi>My leaneneſſe, my leaneneſſe, woe is me: the tranſgreſſours haue offended; yea, the tranſgreſſours haue grieuouſly offended:</hi> He did ſo grieue at the tranſgreſſions of the people, that he became exceeding leane with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as the doubling of the word importeth. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie</hi> likewiſe is full of paſſion in this behalfe,<note place="margin">Ier. 4.19.</note> ſometimes he crieth out, as if he were in great perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>My belly, my belly, I am pained euen at the very heart, my heart is troubled within me, I cannot be ſtill.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he wiſheth that his head were full of water, and his eyes a fountaine of teares, that he might weepe day and night for the ſinnes of the people: and he told them that his ſoule ſhould weepe in ſecret for their Pride,<note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.</note> and his eyes ſhould weepe and drop downe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132056:7"/> teares. How did <hi>Samuel</hi> weepe for the ſinnes of <hi>Saul?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 13.17. 1 Sam. 16.2. Pſal. 119.139.</note> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, that his eyes did guſh out with riuers of water, becauſe men kept not the Law of God. How did <hi>Saint Paul</hi> weepe for them that did walke inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately among the <hi>Philippians?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.18. Ezra. 10.1.</note> How did <hi>Ezra</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good men weepe for the ſinnes of the people in his time? If then theſe good men beholding the ſinnes of the people of their times, and conſidering the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and puniſhments that would fall vpon them, did weepe abundantly: How can we paſſe by our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſinning with an high hand, and committing ſinne with greedineſſe, and not weepe for their ſinnes? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I begin to relate vnto you the ſinnes of this age, and of our Land, I cannot but tremble. How doe men and women, young and old, rich and poore, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally take the holy name of God in vaine? how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is Gods holy Sabaoth prophaned? how many murthers in this land haue beene committed, and the murtherers haue eſcaped? how is adulterie and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication committed, and is not puniſhed? how is theft boulſtered? how doth drunkenneſſe raigne in this land, and is made but a ſport and paſtime? Are not theſe ſinnes like the ſinnes of the firſt age? Haue not the ſinnes of our Land, exceeded the ſinnes of the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites?</hi> and ſhall we not now weepe for the ſinnes of the people of this land? yes, let vs not onely weepe, but let vs houle and cry for them,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.17.</note> as <hi>Ioel</hi> exhorted the people of his time. Now if this be required of vs for other mens ſinnes, much more ſhould we ſorrow and weepe for our owne ſinnes; our ſinnes ſhould be our greateſt ſorrow; nothing in the world ſhould come ſo neere our hearts as they: and therefore the Lord ſaith, that when men are once brought to a true ſight of their ſinnes, they ſhall mourne for them,<note place="margin">Zacha. 12.10.</note> euen as one that mourneth for his onely ſonne; and be ſorry, as one is ſorry for his firſt borne. As nothing more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132056:8"/> woundeth the heart of a tender Father, then to looſe his onely Sonne, the image of his name, and the hope of his houſe: ſo nothing ſhould pierce the heart of a man ſo deepely, as the conſideration of his ſinnes. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weepe in the world, but not for their ſinnes, but for worldly reſpects; ſuch abuſe their teares, as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> vpon the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> doth at large declare. <hi>Many weepe becauſe they cannot haue that which they vniuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 21.4.</note> So mourned <hi>Achab</hi> for <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard. Some weepe becauſe they cannot be reuenged on their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſo did <hi>Eſau</hi> weepe becauſe he could not hurt his brother <hi>Iacob.</hi> Many weepe, becauſe their Parents die not, that they might be their heires, and enioy their goods. Many weepe becauſe they cannot be rich, nor haue the world at wil, as ſome haue: But how few among vs doe weepe for our ſins?<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.6. Pſal. 102.10. Math. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> euery night waſhed his bed, and watered his couch with his teares: <hi>Peter</hi> when he had denied his Maiſter, went out and wept bitterly: <hi>Mary</hi> ſhed ſuch plenty of teares,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.38.</note> as ſhe waſhed our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſts feete with them: And haue not we thinke you as great cauſe to weepe for our owne ſinnes? yes verily, and if we would but enter into our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and call our ſinnes to remembrance, and iudge our ſelues, euery one of vs humbly bowing the knees of our heart, ſhould thus ſay vnto the Lord; O my God, how haue I beſtowed all thoſe Talents of gold which thou haſt giuen me? how haue I requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee for all thy kindneſſe towards me? what hath my whole life beene elſe but a continuall warring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee? O Lord Ieſus, what hath my life beene elſe but a daily renewing of all thy bloudy torments, and of all thy paſſions! Ah vile wretch that I am, how often haue I betrayed thee, and ſould thee for a little worldly pleaſure, or for a little luker and gaine? How often haue I bound thine hands, and euen moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully ſpitefully ſpit in thy face, by refuſing thoſe gifts which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132056:8"/> thou wouldeſt haue giuen thee? how often haue I quenched the good motions of thy ſpirit put into me? For this ſhould I weepe day and night.<note place="margin">
                     <p>In fontem fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, atque in flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umina vertam.</p>
                     <p>Lachrimae nobis deerunt, ante quam cauſae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendi. <hi>Senec. de breui. vitae.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> It is no ſmall meaſure of ſorrow that is ſufficient, in reſpect of the greatneſſe of our ſinnes: For if we had an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth eyes, and ſhould weepe them all out; and if we had a thouſand hearts, and they ſhould all breake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, with remorſe and ſorrow for our ſinnes, it were too little, and we ſhould ſooner want teares, then mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of mourning.</p>
               <p>If we thinke that we ſhould be ſuch vile wretches, as by our ſins to crucifie Chriſt ſo often, and to put him to ſo many deaths, who hath beene to vs ſo kinde a Lord, and ſo louing a Sauiour: For we muſt not thinke that a little ſorrow, or a few teares will ſerue the turne, but we muſt haue great meaſure of griefe; looke how grieuouſly we haue ſinned, ſo grieuouſly ſhould we bewaile our ſinnes. A deepe wound muſt haue a large plaiſter; and our repentance muſt not be leſſe then our fault. It is true, it is no matter of merit for a man to weepe more or leſſe: we may ſay in this caſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.8.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith of meates; <hi>it is not our teares that makes vs acceptable to God:</hi> but yet much ſorrow, and much weeping, in a token of great repentance: and on the other ſide, where there is a little ſorrow, and a little weeping, there is but a little repentance. <hi>Peter</hi> when he had denied his Maiſter, went out and wept bitterly. The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.27.</note> that lamented after the Lord for their ſin, are ſaid to haue poured out buckets of teares, as it were vnto the Lord: and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith that he wept in ſuch abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, as he cauſed his bed to ſwim,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> and watered his couch with his teares. In both which places, though there be an Hyperbolicall exceſſe of ſpeech (for it is not poſſible for men to fill buckets with teares,<note place="margin">Cura dolorque animi, lacrymae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> alimenta fuere. Ouid meta. li. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> nor to cauſe themſelues to ſwimme in their beds) yet it ſignifieth that there was an exceeding great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132056:9"/> meaſure of griefe. Againe, he ſaith, that his teares were his meate,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.3. Luk. 7.38. Ioel. 2.12.</note> day and night: And <hi>Mary,</hi> as before was noted, ſhed ſuch plenty of teares, as ſhee waſhed our Sauiours feete with them. Let vs then I beſeech you,<note place="margin">Weepe for your ſelues, and for your children. Luk. 23.28. A good ſaying of a prophane mouth. <hi>Ille dolet verè qui ſine teſte dolet. Martialis. lib</hi> 1. <hi>Epigra.</hi> 34.</note> turne vnto the Lord with faſting, and with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and with mourning; both for the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for our owne ſinnes. O that I could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thus much of you, or rather of God for you, that you would weepe for your ſinnes, though not at this time, and in this place, yet when you are at home, and by your ſelues, when ye conſider of this ye haue heard this day, that ſo God may regard your teares, put them into his bottle, and auert the iudgements which our ſinnes haue iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
               <p>We haue heard how our Lord Ieſus wept ouer <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> now let vs conſider what <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> did. <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> was ſecure, ſhe reioyced, ſhe was merry, ſhe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no danger, therefore her deſtruction came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly vpon her, and ſhe could not auoide it. This was the ſtate of the firſt age, they ate, they dranke, they bought, they ſould, they married, and were giuen in marriage, and ſodainely the floud came, and ſwept them all away.<note place="margin">This was the ſtate of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoaſt.</note> This was the ſtate of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> they feared no danger, and ſuddenly were conſumed with fire and brimſtone from heauen. This was the ſtate of <hi>Babilon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 47.7.</note> who ſaid, <hi>I ſhall be a Lady for euer:</hi> therefore ſhe gaue her ſelfe to pleaſure, and dwelt careleſſe: ſhe ſaid, <hi>I am, and none elſe, I ſhall not ſit as a widow, neither ſhall know the loſſe of children.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">8.</note> But what ſaid the Lord? <hi>now heare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe two things ſhall come to thee ſuddenly in one day, the loſſe of children and widowhood, they ſhall come vpon thee in their perfection, for the multitude of thy diuinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and for the great abundance of thy Inchanters. Saint Iohn</hi> likewiſe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.7.8. Luk. 12.19.20.</note> in the Reuelation, propheſied in like manner of her. This was the ſtate of the rich man in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132056:9"/> the Goſpell, who promiſed to himſelfe many dayes,<note place="margin">Of the rich Glutton. Luk. 18.</note> and yet the ſame night his ſoule was fetcht away. This was the errour of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſaid in his proſperity, he ſhould neuer be remoued; but he retracted it, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the contrary. Now here we haue a true diſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, and of the times wherein we liue; we haue inioyed ſuch a long peace, as neither our Fathers, nor our forefathers euer knew; we haue had ſo long proſperitie, we haue had ſo great plenty of all things; but aboue all theſe, we haue had the Goſpell and word of God ſo plentifully, and ſo ſincerely preached among vs, as ſcarce hath beene ſeene in any age heretofore. Now theſe Halcion daies, this long peace, this great proſperitie, makes men ſecure, they thinke this will euer hold, they feare no alteration, they thinke they ſtand immoueable: this was the ſtate of former times, and they ſmarted for their ſecuritie, and vaine confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, let vs then take heede and be wiſe,<note place="margin">Omnium rerum eſt viciſſitudo.</note> let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the change of all things is ſudden, if God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into iudgement with vs, if he hide his face from vs, we ſhall be changed, and our proſperitie may be turned into aduerſity, &amp; our ioy into mourning.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.37.38.</note> Our Lord Ieſus foretould the ſecuritie of the world, before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that it ſhould be as it was in the time of <hi>Noah.</hi> And <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>When they ſhall ſay peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theſ. 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then ſhall ſuddow deſtruction come vpon them, as the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile vpon a woman, and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi> Let vs not then flatter our ſelues with theſe goodly daies, but let vs feare an alteration, let vs like good Seruants be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready with our accompt in our hands, and like wiſe Virgins, with oyle in our Lampes, that no ſudden change may ouertake vs, nor any aduerſitie diſmay vs, but that we may ſay in any aduerſe hap that may befall vs, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, <hi>that is come vpon me that I was affraid of. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:132056:10"/>
               <head>Saying, O if thou hadſt knowne, at the leaſt in this thy day, thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace.</head>
               <p>IN theſe words our Sauiour Chriſt doth complaine, and vpbraide the blindeneſſe of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> His words are paſſionate, therefore abrupt: for we know in whom earneſt affections meete, being ſurpriſed with griefe, they cannot vtter their whole minde, but breake off abruptly. Chriſt then doth not onely complaine, and pitty the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but doth alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide this ingratefull people, their great wickedneſſe in reiecting ſaluation offered, and drawing wittingly the heauie iudgement of God vpon them. For it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like that this thought did diſquiet the minde of our Lord Ieſus. Behold, O daughter <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> I come vnto thee, thy King, and thy Sauiour, as the Prophet promiſed thee; but poore, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, therefore thou deſpiſeſt me, from whoſe hand thou mighteſt receiue righteouſneſſe, &amp; euerlaſting life. I would thou hadſt knowne thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace, and wert not blinde in thine owne euill, and in this thy day, wherein ſo many and ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things doe call thee to the knowledge of theſe things. For now thou haſt mee preaching vnto thee the kingdome of heauen, the day of ſaluation and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation is riſen vpon thee, which thou oughteſt to know by my doctrine, and miracles wrought before thy eyes, in the middeſt of thee. But O thriſe, and foure times vnhappy, theſe things are hid from thee, thou doeſt maliciouſly blinde thy ſelfe, that thou mighteſt not ſee them; therefore thou doeſt rage, and art mad againſt me, and ſeekeſt my bloud, whom with an earneſt affection, thou ſhouldeſt receiue and embrace as thy Sauiour.</p>
               <p>By this then it appeareth, that our Lord Ieſus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132056:10"/> againſt the blindneſſe, ſtubborneneſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that by no admonitions, no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, nay, not with teares, ſhe would not be mollifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor warned, to auoide her future calamities. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Simile. </seg>
                  </label> For euen as a good Father, labouring to draw a ſtubborne and diſobedient Sonne to grace and goodneſſe, by all good meanes, but doth not preuaile, hath the greater cauſe to complaine: euen ſo our Lord Ieſus had great cauſe to complaine againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not conſidering the grace that was offered vnto her.</p>
               <p>And this affection of ſo great mercy which we ſee was in Chriſt the Sonne of God, the like we reade that God the Father doth declare to be in himſelfe, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of the Scriptures. As when he complained againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> for their ſtubborneneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, he ſaith thus:<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that my people had harkned vnto me, and Iſrael had walked in my wayes. I would ſoone haue humbled their enemies, and turned my hand againſt their aduerſaries.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">15.</note> 
                  <hi>The haters of God ſhould haue beene ſubiect vnto him, and their time ſhould haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for euer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">16.</note> 
                  <hi>And God would haue fed them with the fat of wheate, and with honey out of the rocke would I haue ſatisfied thee.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 48.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that they were wiſe. then they would vnderſtand this, they would conſider their latter end.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 32.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them to feare me, and to keepe all my commandements alway: that it might goe well with them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 5.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and with their children for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Scriptures it is euident, that mans perdition is of himſelfe, and in himſelfe, and not of God.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13 9. Eze. 33.11. Pro. 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, O Iſrael, is of thy ſelfe, but thy helpe is in me. I liue</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I would not the death of a ſinner. I haue called</hi> ſaith wiſedome, <hi>and ye haue refuſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Ieruſalem,</hi> ſaith our Lord Ieſus, <hi>how often would I haue gathered thee together, as a henne doth her chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, and thou wouldeſt not.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> God would haue all men
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132056:11"/> to be ſaued,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> and to come to the knowledge of the truth: Here then thoſe wicked and prophane men are to be reproued, who aſcribe their damnation to God, when it is in themſelues. For God cals, and they ſtop their eares, like the deafe Adder, and will not heare: God offers grace, and they refuſe it: God warnes them of their miſeries to come, if they doe not repent; but they will not beleeue and turne to God, but harden their hearts, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, till deſtruction come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thou.</head>
               <p>THis word <hi>(Thou)</hi> is emphaticall, for euery word in the Scriptures hath his weight, and euery ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable his ſence. <hi>Oh that thou,</hi> thou <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whom God hath choſen to be his ſanctuary, to be his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place, to put his name there, with whom hee hath made a couenant, vpon whom hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſo many benefits, whom he hath hedged about, and defended againſt all enemies: Oh that thou, which in priuiledges and prerogatiues excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt all the Cities in the world, <hi>hadst knowne the things that belong vnto thy peace.</hi> Other Cities haue knowne their peace, and the time of their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in mercie; as <hi>Niniuie,</hi> who repented at the preaching of <hi>Ionah.</hi> Oh that thou wert in the number of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>Here the Miniſters and Preachers of Gods word, are taught to apply their admonitions to the whole Nation; yea, to particular Cities; yea, to particular Townes; yea, to particular perſons: when they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and obſtinately reiect the grace and mercy of God, then they may iuſtly complaine againſt them, and fitly vſe this manner of ſpeaking; <hi>Oh that thou hadst knowne the things that concerne thy peace.</hi> Oh that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132056:11"/> thou Adulterer, Oh that thou Drunkard, Oh that thou Blaſphemer, Oh that thou prophaner of Gods Sabboath, Oh that thou Vſurer, thou Oppreſſour, wouldeſt feare the iudgements that will light vpon thee, if thou knoweſt not the things that belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy peace, and doſt not by true repentance turne vnto God whiles he doth ſpeake vnto thee, and warne thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hadſt knowne.</head>
               <p>OVr Lord Ieſus wiſheth that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had knowne the things that belong vnto her peace. Whence we learne that knowledge is an excellent thing; wee ſhould all labour for to attaine vnto it. For to know God and Ieſus Chriſt, to know the myſteries of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to know the things that belong vnto our peace; to know the time of our viſitation, in mercie; this is mans <hi>Summum bonum;</hi> his happineſſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> his glory. This is life eternall, to know thee, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt. Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength; nor the rich man in his riches;<note place="margin">Ier. 9.24.</note> but let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he knoweth me to be the Lord: for I deſire mercy, and not ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.6.</note> and the knowledge of God, more then burnt offerings, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Oh that thou hadst knowne,</hi> ſaith our Lord Ieſus to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And may not we ſay to <hi>England;</hi> yea, to <hi>London;</hi> yea, may not euery Miniſter and Preacher of the word, ſay to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular place, where hee is reſiant; Oh that thou hadſt knowne the things wherein thy peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:132056:12"/>
               <head>At the leaſt in this thy day.</head>
               <p>IN theſe words is an Amplification taken from the time. As if our Lord Ieſus ſhould ſay, hitherto thou haſt beene obſtinate and ſtubborne, thou haſt killed my Prophets which I ſent vnto thee; thou haſt often hitherto reiected me: Oh that now, in this thy day, which my Father hath appointed to call thee by me, thou wouldeſt be wiſe and know thy time. The ſpeech of our Sauiour Chriſt containeth an exclamation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from his heart, and vttered with ſo great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of dolour, that he could not perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, but breaketh it off, euen as when a man is in great heauineſſe and ſorrow, intending to vtter his griefe, he is inforced to breake it off abruptly. In this ſpeech our Lord Ieſus admoniſheth, that the day was come which God in his eternall counſell had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the ſaluation of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by the Prophets; which opportunitie, if ſhe did not lay hold on, the gate of ſaluation ſhould be ſhut againſt her for euer. This kinde of ſpeech is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the Scriptures:<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.8. 2 Cor. 6.2. Iſa. 8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Now the acceptable time, now is the day of ſaluation.</hi> Againe, <hi>Seeke the Lord whiles he may be found, call vpon him whiles he is neere. And that conſidering the ſeaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.11.</note> 
                  <hi>that it is now time that we ſhould ariſe from ſleepe, for now is our ſaluation neerer, then when we beleeued.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">12.</note> 
                  <hi>The night is paſt, and the day is at hand, let vs therefore caſt away the workes of darkeneſſe, and put vpon vs the armour of light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>Here then we learne, that when God giueth men a day wherein God doth call them, it is not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, not to be let ſlip. Now God calleth men two waies: Firſt, by his iudgements: ſecondly, by his mercies: And the word <hi>(day)</hi> is ſo taken, both for the iudgement of God, and alſo for the mercy of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132056:12"/> God. In the firſt kinde God doth call by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by warre, by famine,<note place="margin">Aut terrendo minis, aut cordeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do flagellis, aut blandiendo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficijs. <hi>Flugo in Cant. 1.</hi>
                  </note> by peſtilence and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by captiuitie, for when God doth chaſtiſe and puniſh vs, he calleth vs to repentance: In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kinde, God doth call vs by mercy, and clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; and he calleth vs more openly at one time, then he doth at another. Sometimes he ſeemeth to forſake his Church, as if the truth were altogether extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; as he did when the <hi>Pope</hi> raigned in all places, almoſt through Chriſtendome: But now he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs his Goſpel, he doth reach his hand of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vnto vs. This then is a mercifull calling, vnto the which, except we obay, there remaineth no excuſe for vs hereafter. God doth now then call vs by his Goſpell, and he hath called vs many yeares: Now is our time, now is the day of Saluation; O three times happy we, if we know it, if we lay hold on it, before it is paſt, before it ſlip away. The day, when it is paſt, cannot be called againe; when the day of mercy is paſt, then commeth the day of iudgement, which cannot be auoided. I beſeech ye therefore brethren, by the mercies of God, in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, that ye would diligently conſider theſe things, that ye would know this acceptable time, this day of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it be not iuſtly ſaid vnto you, <hi>Oh that ye had knowne, at the leaſt in this your day, the things that belong vnto your peace.</hi> Our Fathers and Forefathers neuer had ſo great mercy ſhewed vnto them, as we haue; they had not the Goſpell ſo plentifully and ſincerely preached vnto them, as we haue; therefore except we repent, and be conuerted, we ſhall be the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſhed. The fault is increaſed by circumſtance of the time, and the puniſhment of the fault, is greater, or leſſe by degrees: Therefore the neerer God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto vs, and doth offer vnto vs the light of his Goſpell, if we neglect it, or deſpiſe it, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132056:13"/> no excuſe; for God will ſay, I haue called, and ye refuſed,<note place="margin">Pro. 1. Iere. 22.21. Zacha. 7.13.</note> I offered grace vnto you, and you would not embrace it: therefore ye ſhall cry, and I will not heare you. To day therefore, whiles it is to day, heare his voyce, and harden not your hearts, leſt yee prouoke Gods wrath, and draw great puniſhments vpon you.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we heare learne the great mercy of God receiuing men euen at the laſt vnto repentance: For God is long ſuffering,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> patient, and ſlow vnto wrath, he waiteth for vs long, and expecteth our conuerſion euery day, and receiueth vs to mercy, though it be late or we repent. Oh the great mercy and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able clemencie of God toward ſinners! He receiued the theefe on the croſſe to mercy at the laſt houre; he receiued the Prodigall childe to mercy, though it were long ere he returned. This is a Doctrine conſolatory, if it be taken aright, but alas, there are too many that abuſe it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> The wicked, becauſe God holdeth his peace, and is long ſuffering, in waiting for their conuerſion, they thinke God to be like vnto themſelues, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage themſelues to miſchiefe, and take liberty to ſinne;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Knoweſt thou not,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long ſuffering of God, doth leade thee vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5.</note> but <hi>thou after the hardneſſe of thy heart, that cannot repent, heapeſt vnto thy ſelfe wrath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the day of wrath, and of the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God, who will reward euery man according to his workes.</hi> Let vs not then abuſe the patience of God, neither let vs preſume of his mercy, for as he is mercifull, ſo he is iuſt. This point is to be preſſed againſt thoſe that crie God is mercifull, God is mercifull, and ſay that it ſufficeth if in the laſt houre they can ſay, <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon me:</hi> But this is an vngodly preſumption; for hath God promiſed to any that time to preſume of it? nay, many times ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132056:13"/> doth prouoke Gods wrath againſt ſuch ſinners, that he taketh them ſuddenly away, that they cannot vtter one word: Therefore that good father ſaid well of the two theeues which were hanged with Chriſt, one was ſaued, that no man ſhould deſpaire, and the other condemned, that no man ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume. This example is but one, therefore let vs not preſume; and it is generally held, that <hi>Qualis vita, finis ita;</hi> as men liue, ſo commonly they die. And it is ſaid, <hi>Paenitentia ſera, raro eſt vera:</hi> Late repentance, is ſeldome true repentance. But another Father ſaith thus, <hi>Hoc prorſus affirmo, hoc audio dicere, nunquam malo mori po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, qui bene vixit:</hi> This I altogether affirme, this I dare bouldly ſay, he neuer can die ill, that hath liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed well. Let the mercy of God then this day leade vs to repentance, that we may ſerue him from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our life, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thoſe things which belong vnto thy peace.</head>
               <p>OVr Lord Ieſus wiſhed that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> knew thoſe things that did concerne her peace. The word <hi>Peace,</hi> among the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> doth deſigne all the parts of felicitie. Neither doth he ſay ſimply that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> knew not her peace, but <hi>the things that did belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her peace.</hi> Becauſe many times men know their happineſſe, but being blinded with malice, they knew not the way, nor the meanes vnto it. As for example: All men confeſſe that it is mans happineſſe to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with God, and yet reiect and contemne the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which is the meanes to obtaine it. Our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and his Apoſtles preached the Goſpell vnto <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> but ſhe deſpiſed it, therefore ſhe did not know the things which concerned her peace.</p>
               <p>Here then we learne, that the word of God, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132056:14"/> the Goſpell of Chriſt where it is preached, doth bring with it true peace, true happineſſe, and doth offer it vnto men. It procureth outward peace, and inward peace. In a word, the Goſpell of Chriſt doth make a Citie, a Policie, a Kingdome, and Region to flouriſh, and maketh a People happy: Therefore happy are they which beleeue that the word of God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in it <hi>thoſe things which belong vnto their peace;</hi> that is, vnto perfect and eternall felicitie. And that this doctrine may appeare to be moſt true, if we a little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the writings of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, we ſhall ſee plainely, that no kingdome nor policy can flouriſh, that no King, no Potentate, nor People can be wiſe; nor bleſſed in their gouernment, which haue not the word of God to direct and guide them. It hath beene the iudgement and opinion almoſt of all wiſe men in the world, that Kings and Kingdomes of the world were moſt happy, if the King of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie were wiſe; if he had many aged, graue, wiſe, and faithfull Counſellours; if his Captaines were valerous, couragious, expert, and fortunate in warre: If he abounded in wealth; if his kingdome were euery-where well fortified. Laſtly, if his People and Subiects were peaceable, and agreed together: I confeſſe that all theſe things are rightly, truely, and wiſely ſpoken; yet the chiefe and moſt excellent of all, is not mentioned, without the which no true felicitie is obtained, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gotten, cannot be ſafely preſerued and kept: on the otherſide, where this alone is preſent, all other thing neceſſary for man, doe accompany it and follow. Our Lord and God therefore, who is the onely giuer of wiſe and perfect counſell, doth briefely and ſhortly knit all theſe things together in the Goſpell, and his holy word: Firſt, <hi>Seeke the kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and all other things ſhall be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto you. Mat.</hi> 6. Therefore our Lord Ieſus ſaid
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132056:14"/> thus to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are your eyes which ſee the things that you ſee; for I ſay vnto you that many Kings and Prophets, haue deſired to ſee the things which you ſee, and haue not ſeene them; and to heare the things which you heare, and haue not heard them.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that heare the word of God, and keepe it.</hi> And this one thing aboue all other things, is moſt neceſſary; <hi>Mary hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not be taken from her.</hi> I dare therefore confidently affirme out of the word of God, that thoſe Kings ſhall flouriſh, and inioy a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py eſtate, which doe wholy giue and ſubmit themſelues, and their kingdomes vnto Ieſus Chriſt, the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne of God, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, acknowledging him to be the moſt mighty Prince and greateſt Monarch of all; and themſelues to be his ſeruants and ſubiects, in all their affaires and buſineſſes, not following their owne minde and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor the traditions and lawes of men contrary to the ſtatutes of God, nor good intentions, hauing no good warrant out of the word of God, but in all things ſubmitting themſelues vnto Chriſt, the king of the Church, and endeuouring to ſubdue all their people to the lawes of this king, and ſo doing, they, their people, and their kingdomes ſhall flouriſh. For ſo the Lord himſelfe hath ſpoken, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18. <hi>When the King ſhall ſit in the throne of his kingdome, and ſhall ſet before him the example of this Law, in this booke, let it be with him, and let him reade in it all the dayes of his life. Verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>And let him not depart from this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either to the right hand, or to the left, that he may prolong his dayes in his kingdome, he and his ſonnes in the middeſt of Iſrael.</hi> So likewiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. vnto the ſixt. Againe, <hi>Let not this booke of the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of thy mouth, but meditate in it day and night, that thou mayſt carefully doe as it is written therein, then ſhalt thou proſper in thy waies, and all ſhall goe well with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132056:15"/> thee. Ioſu.</hi> 1.8. Whereby it appeareth that the felicitie and proſperitie of Kings, Princes, People, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, doe depend vpon the word of God, and haue promiſes of bleſſings, both in this life, and in the life to come. And now we will proue it by examples. <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was ſo long happy and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of his enemies, as he obeyed the word of God, but when he yeelded to his good intentions, contrary to Gods word and commandement; <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid vnto him, <hi>Thou haſt plaid the foole, thou haſt forſaken the word of the Lord, and the Lord hath forſaken thee, that thou ſhouldeſt not be King of Iſrael.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.26. Now how great the miſery of <hi>Saul</hi> was afterward, the ſtorie doth euidently declare. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſucceeded him next in the Kingdome, who was moſt happy in his kingdome. But how greatly he eſteemed the word of God, it may appeare in the booke of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> eſpecially in the 119. <hi>Pſalme;</hi> for from his priuate euils, from his euill actions committed againſt the word of God, and from the vnnaturall inſurrection of his Son <hi>Abſolon</hi> againſt him, he had learned how great a ſinne, and how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious an euill it was to decline from the word of God. <hi>Salomon</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Dauid</hi> the moſt wiſe, and moſt excellent King of all the world, did ſo long inioy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and was commended of the Lord, as he did reuerently obey the word of God: but when he once began to reiect the word of God, the Lord by and by ſaid vnto him, <hi>Becauſe this was in thy heart, that thou haſt not kept my couenant, and my ſtatutes, which I haue commanded thee, I will rent thy Kingdome from thee, and giue it to thy Seruant.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.11. And this preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came to paſſe after the death of <hi>Salomon.</hi> The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was rent into two parts, ten Tribes followed <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> the Seruant of <hi>Salomon;</hi> and two Tribes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleaued to <hi>Roboam</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who for the contempt of Gods word and following ſtrangers,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132056:15"/> was ouerwhelmed with many euils. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.5. Therefore <hi>Shemaiaeh</hi> the Prophet ſaid vnto <hi>Roboam,</hi> and to the Princes of <hi>Iudah;</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>You haue forſaken me, therefore I doe alſo forſake you, leauing you to the hands of Shiſhacke.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Abia</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Roboam</hi> ouercame the armie of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though more in number, and greater in ſtrength, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he truſted in the word of the Lord. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 13.15. So <hi>Aſa</hi> proſpered in peace and tranquility forty yeares, becauſe he ſuppreſſed Idolatry, and ſuperſtition, and reſtored the ſincere religion of God. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 14. So <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. This is alſo diligently noted in the liues of the reſt of the Kings, as in <hi>Ioram,</hi> in <hi>Ocho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> 4 <hi>King.</hi> 9. In <hi>Ioas,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 23.24. In <hi>Amaſia,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 25. In <hi>Oſia,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 26. In <hi>Iothan,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 27. In <hi>Achaz,</hi> ibidem. In <hi>Ezechiah.</hi> In <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and the reſt, vntill the carying away into captiuitie, both of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of <hi>Iuda;</hi> for ſo long did they flouriſh, and proſper, as they did cleaue to the word of the Lord; but when they contemned and forſooke the word of the Lord, they fell into great miſery and ruine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hence we may collect that the ground, foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and continuance of all happineſſe, peace and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie of Kings and Kingdomes, doth conſiſt in the word of God, and the obedience thereunto: and on the other ſide, the ruine and confuſion of Kings and Kingdomes, is in the contempt and forſaking of the word of God: And why ſo? becauſe the Lord ſaith, <hi>They that honour me, I will honour, but they that deſpiſe me, I will deſpiſe.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</p>
               <p>But leauing theſe examples, which doe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirme this truth; Let vs conſider of ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne and late examples, whereof we haue beene eye-witneſſes: How did God bleſſe our late noble Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that againe he might ſeale the truth of this doctrine to all the world: <hi>Bleſſed is that Prince whoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132056:16"/> God is the Lord. Pſal.</hi> 144.15. How plentifully did God bleſſe her, and her people, aboue all Kings and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with peace and plenty? according to the Prayer in the Pſalme, for <hi>Ieruſalem. Pſal.</hi> 122. For ſhe, and we her people did inioy ſuch peace and ſuch plenty, as our forefathers neuer knew, nor Chronicles doe record to haue beene in the time of our aunceſtours, in times paſt. Our Land did yeelde abundance of all things which grew at home; and forraigne Nations did mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter plenty of other commodities growing abroad: So that whatſoeuer from the Eaſt, to the Weſt, whatſoeuer was vnder heauen, was brought home vnto vs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Land hath beene greatly inriched: The peace of our Country is meruailous in ſo long and continuall troubles of our neighbour Countries round about vs, and in ſo many conſultations and deuiſes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the diſturbance of our peace, and the ruine of our Countrie. Moreouer God did giue vnto her Maieſtie, ſuch honour and renowne, that ſhe ſat as a Iudge, and an honourable Arbitratour in the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and controuerſies of the mightieſt Monarches and Potentates of Europe, and of all her Neighbours: Now what was the cauſe of ſo great peace, of ſo great treaſure, and of ſo great honour? Verily the Word of God, which her highneſſe receiued, embraced, and promoted to the vttermoſt of her power. Now after all theſe, though the Papiſts deuiſed and plotted her death, and many were ſuborned and hired by the <hi>Pope,</hi> a man of ſinne, a maintainer of rebellion and murther (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſheweth of what ſpirit he is) yet God brought her to the graue in peace, by naturall death, full of dayes: And after her, God hath giuen vnto vs a wiſe, gracious, and Religious King, our King <hi>Iames,</hi> whom God brought into the Land ſo peaceably, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of forraigne Nations, and to the great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vs all: and he, to the great comfort of all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132056:16"/> Chriſtians, loueth the Goſpell and word of GOD, maintaineth it to his vttermoſt power, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the true worſhip of God, to all his people. And how hath God protected him, both in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and here in <hi>England</hi> againſt the wicked Papiſts, who with bloudy and murthering hearts, deuiſed ſuch a diuelliſh and inhumane ſtratagem, to ouerthrow him and his iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and to deſtroy the flouriſhing ſtate of <hi>England:</hi> ſo that if God had not beene on our ſide, both his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, his royall and hopefull progeny; and all we that loue the Goſpell had beene ſwallowed vp, and made a prey to their teeth. Happy therefore we, if we know our happineſſe, bleſſed are we, <hi>if we know the things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But now they are hid from thy eyes.</head>
               <p>OVr Lord Ieſus firſt ſent his Prophets to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> at length he came in his owne perſon (for <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> killed and ſtoned his Prophets) therefore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and in the middeſt of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> among all the people he doth many miracles, which the Prophets foretold ſhould be wrought by the <hi>Meſſias</hi> when he came, he preacheth the Goſpell to them, wherewith hee laboured to gather them together <hi>as a Henne doth her Chickens,</hi> and wherein her happineſſe conſiſted,<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> as we haue heard; yet all theſe things were hidden from the eyes of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt here ſaith. This is not ſpoken to extenuate, or leſſen the fault of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but rather in reproach, her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull blockiſhneſſe is noted, that ſhe did not ſee God preſent: For how could <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> be ignorant of Gods will, which daily had the promiſes of ſaluation in her mouth; and to whom the Law was often repeated? Could the <hi>Iewes</hi> be ignorant of Chriſt, who was many yeeres conuerſant among them, ſhewing forth his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132056:17"/> ſauing power, not onely in teaching, but in working many wonderfull workes and miracles among them? Therefore our Lord Ieſus in theſe words, doth note their blockiſhnes, and wilfull blindneſſe, wherewith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hindred, they could not ſee God offering himſelfe vnto them, nor yet obſerue his mercy, nor manifeſt arguments of his wrath. Chriſt therefore here doth teach, that the Citizens of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were authors of their owne deſtruction, as alſo healeth a ſcandall which roſe from their voluntary and wilfull ignorance. For without doubt, many were detained and kept backe, by the example of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> from embracing Chriſt, and receiuing his Goſpell, which they ſaw were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected of them, who bare the chiefe eſtimation of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and wiſedome: He therefore doth admoniſh that their incredulity and contumacy ſhould not offend any, who being wilfully blinded with their owne pride and blockiſhneſſe, did draw vpon themſelues Gods wrath, and their owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Let vs now apply this vnto our ſelues, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider, whether it be not our caſe. Our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus by the preaching of his Goſpell, hath manifeſted vnto vs his loue, hath reuealed vnto vs his kindneſſe, hath with his Goſpell giuen vnto vs a long peace, and innumerable bleſſings; but men are ſo beſotted with the vanities of the world, and ſo blinded with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life, that they winke with their eyes, that they cannot ſee, and ſtop their eares, like the deafe Adder, that they cannot heare the ſweet voyce of Chriſt calling and alluring them: For it cannot be but men maliciouſly blinde themſelues, ſeeing <hi>the grace of God that bringeth ſaluation to all men hath appeared, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men to deny vngodlineſſe, and worldy luſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to liue ſoberly, iuſtly, and godly in this preſent world. Tit.</hi> 2.11.<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> Therefore if men now are blinde,<note place="margin">Deu. 30.11. Rom. 10.6.7.8.</note> if they be ignorant of ſo great fauours of God, whereof we haue beene
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:132056:17"/> eye-witneſſes, and haue taſted of the good word of God, there is no excuſe to be pretended. But we may ſay to them, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Corinthians, If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the mindes:</hi> that is, <hi>of Infidels, that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt, which is the Image of God ſhould not ſhine vnto them.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3.4. This is a great iudgement, wherewith God doth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the wicked contemners of his word, when the eyes of their minde are blinded, that they ſee not God preſent, not taſte his mercies, nor feare the puniſhments that are imminent and neere at hand.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures teacheth vs, that no ignorance is excuſable: <hi>for he that knoweth not his Maiſters will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be beaten, though with few ſtripes,</hi> becauſe ignorance is not of creation, but of deprauation and corruption of nature: <hi>But he that knoweth his Maiſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes,</hi> becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not excuſe himſelfe; therefore wilfull ignorance, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary blindneſſe is inexcuſable, and ſhall be the more ſeuerely puniſhed. Here then that groſe errour of the Papiſts is conuinced, who affirme without wit or bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ignorance is the mother of deuotion;<note place="margin">Math. 22.29.</note> but it may better be called the mother of errour, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, becauſe it leadeth men to perdition and eternall puniſhments: for if eternall life conſiſt in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3. then eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death abideth them which know not God, nor his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. If the wiſe man ought not to glory in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, nor the rich man in his riches; but ſhould glory that he knoweth and vnderſtandeth the Lord, to exerciſe mercy, righteouſneſſe and iudgement. <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.23.24. Then whoſoeuer is ignorant of God and his will, and knowes not Chriſt the Sonne of God, ſhould lament and be ſorry that theſe things are hid from his eyes,
<pb facs="tcp:132056:18"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:132056:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
